Guide to the Annie Burr Lewis Papers
The Lewis Walpole Library
- Correspondence, 1900–1960; Series I; 10.56; 15 boxes
  - Service and Affiliations
    - Yale University
      - Faculty Committee for Receiving Oxford and Cambridge University Children
        Beginning in July 1940, the Yale Faculty Committee for Receiving Oxford and Cambridge University Children coordinated the wartime evacuation of wives of Oxford faculty members and their children to Connecticut. More than 125 mothers and children arrived in New Haven; Annie Lewis sponsored three families and provided housing and support in Farmington, taking a personal interest in their well-being during their time in Connecticut in addition to funding the children's education. Iris Johnston and Elizabeth Haslam-Jones, with their children, came under Mrs. Lewis's care. After Haslam-Jones returned to England in the spring of 1942, Irene Ewert and her two daughters took her place. The families were housed at 144 Main Street in Farmington.
        Three other women, Katherine Burn, Brenda Clapham, Ruth McGregor, and their children also came to Farmington under the sponsorship of Robert Keep, the headmaster of Miss Porter's School and his wife RoseAnne.
        - Administrative correspondence, 1940–1944 (Box 10, Folder 3)
        - Burn family, 1940–1941 (Box 10, Folder 4)
          Katherine Pemberton Burn, the wife of Joshua Harold Burn, Professor of Pharmacology, arrived in Farmington with her children Josephine, Margaret ("Molly"), Frances, and Robert.
        - Johnston family, 1940–1958 (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
          Iris May Johnston, the wife of Edward Hamilton Johnston, Boden Professor of Sanskrit at Oxford, arrived with five of their six children: Felicity, Katherine, Veronica, Stephen, and Edward Alexander. Professor Johnston died in October 1942, while his family was living in Farmington.
        - Other families, 1940–1943 (Box 10, Folder 7)
        - London Union of Girls Clubs, 1940–1941 (Box 10, Folder 8)
        - "Oxington Magazine", 1940 (Box 10, Folder 9)
          Two issues of a "magazine" created by the British children living in Farmington; number 1 is a photostat copy, number 2 is a mimeograph copy.
        - Photographs, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 10)
          Snapshot photographs of the English children, without captions.
        - Wooden bowl, 1942 (Box 55)
          Hand painted by Felicity Johnston at a camp in Milton, Vermont, in the summer of 1942.
      - School of Nursing, 1948–1955 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Yale University Art Gallery, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Other correspondence, 1957–1959 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Personal Papers, 1902–1960; Series II; 9.52; 13 boxes
  Series II is organized into eight subseries: Appointment Calendars and Diaries; Awards, Certificates, and Honors; Cookbooks and Recipes; Research Materials; School Notebooks; Scrapbooks and Albums; Writings; and Other Papers.
  The series holds a variety of materials spanning Annie Lewis's life, including her certificates of her birth, baptism, and marriage, school notebooks, postcard albums, scrapbooks, diaries, passports, address books, family recipe books, and copies of her will. Also here are samples of her stationery and records of her purchase of the Hart-Deming house, known as the "Red House," in Farmington that she restored and donated to Miss Porter's School.
  - Appointment Calendars and Diaries
    - Travel diary, 1913–1915 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      Covers two trips: New York-Edinburgh-Strathpeffer-London-New York (1913), and New York-Niagara Falls-Seattle-Western Canada-Montreal-Boston-Newport (1915).
    - Itinerary of a trip to France, Germany, Belgium, and the Netherlands, 1920 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Poems of Today memorandum book, 1930 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      Gift of Corine Roosevelt Robinson to Annie Lewis, and featuring a poem by her.
    - Dream diaries, 1931, undated (Box 12, Folder 4-5)
      Six small notebooks, one dated on cover "March 1931," in which Annie Lewis recorded her dreams.
    - Pocket diaries, 1936–1957 (Box 12, Folder 6-7)
      Small personal appointment books, the same type as used by Wilmarth Lewis (LWL MSS 20, Boxes 262-263), but are here only for the years 1936, 1938, 1939, 1944, 1949, and 1957.
      The pictorial weekly desk calendars kept by Annie Lewis from 1940 until her death in 1959 were continued after her death by Wilmarth Lewis or household staff members. They are filed in the Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Papers (LWL MSS 20), Boxes 264-265.
  - Awards, Certificates, and Honors
    - American National Red Cross, 1917 May 29 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      Certificate for "Elementary Hygiene and Home Care of the Sick" issued after a series of classes taken in New York; with Annie Lewis's autograph outline/notes.
    - Connecticut Society of the Colonial Dames of America, 1929 April 9 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1946 June 24 (Box 54 (Oversize), Folder 2)
      Life membership certificate.
    - Mount Vernon Ladies Association, 1942 May 19 (Box 54 (Oversize), Folder 3)
      Appointment as Vice Regent for the State of Connecticut
    - Yale University, 1949 February 12 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      Resolution in gratitude for the Annie Burr Lewis Fund.
    - New York Botanical Garden, 1950 July 30 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      Membership certificate.
    - Yale University, 1957 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      Filed here is a resolution for Annie Lewis's appointment as Curator of Prints at the Lewis Walpole Library.
    - Alumnae Association of Miss Porter's School, Inc., 1963 (Box 12, Folder 13)
      Posthumous citation to honor her founding the association in 1937.
  - Cookbooks and Recipes
    - Recipe book, 1940s–1950s (Box 12, Folder 14)
      Small three-ring binder with typed recipes and clipped recipes taped on lined pages; some recipes annotated by Annie Lewis. Inserted between the pages are mimeographed sheets of recipes issued by the Home Institute of the New York Herald Tribune.
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Annie Lewis's recipe book was given to Rebecca Sherrill More by Wilmarth Lewis in 1972; she returned it to the library in 2013.
    - Recipe file, 1940s–1950s (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
      A set of index cards with typed recipes.
      Annie Lewis's recipe file was given to Rebecca Sherrill More by Wilmarth Lewis in 1972; she returned it to the library in 2013.
    - Auchincloss family recipes, 1940s–1950s (Box 13, Folder 3)
      Three-ring binder holding typed recipes following a cover sheet with a note in Annie Lewis's hand: "Grandmother Auchincloss's Cook-book (Elizabeth Buck Auchincloss) 1816-1902, the original owned by the late Dr. Hugh Auchincloss. Some of the later entries in the book came from my mother Mrs. Hugh D. Auchincloss." Inserted in back pocket is a separate booklet: "Copies of Recipes (Mary Finnegan) Aunt Annie Burr Jennings' cook."
      A second notebook is a typed copy of the first.
  - Research Materials
    - Notes on book history, collation, and cataloging, 1927, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
      Autograph and typed notes from a course/courses on the history of printing, manuscripts, and creating catalog records.
    - Address book for the eighteenth century, circa 1930 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      Small address book in which Annie Lewis entered names, life dates, addresses, and brief biographies of people in Horace Walpole's circle.
    - Notes on prints, 1957 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      Prints examined at the Fitzwilliam Museum, Dunster Castle, and Sir John Soane Museum.
    - Notes on botanical prints and drawings, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - School Notebooks
    Annie Burr Auchincloss attended Miss Porter's School for three academic years, 1917-1920.
    - Photograph compilations
      - "Spanish Art", 1914 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - "History of Sculpture", 1917 (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - French art, circa 1917 (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - Italian art, circa 1918 (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - "Art Note-Book", 1917 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Modern history notes, 1919 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Hostess notes/recipe book, circa 1919 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbooks and Albums
    The subseries contains four commercial albums and two scrapbooks. The albums hold unsent postcards collected by Annie Lewis on her travels and those she received from family and friends. Because they are fastened to the pages in her arrangement, the cards were unable to be analyzed for content, but it appears that many were sent to Annie by her aunt Annie Burr Jennings (1855-1939). The span dates of albums were determined by postal frankings or datelines that could be easily seen without damaging the cards or pages.
    - Album, 1907–1910 (Box 16)
      Postcards from friends and family, primarily holiday cards.
    - Album, 1907–1910 (Box 17)
      Postcards primarily collected on trips to France and Italy.
    - Album, 1909–1912 (Box 18)
      Postcards collected on trips to England, and received from traveling friends.
    - Album, 1915 (Box 19)
      Postcards collected on trip from Niagara Falls to western Canada.
    - Scrapbook, 1916–1917 (Box 20)
      Covers Esther Auchincloss's wedding to Edmund Nash (1917), and social activities in Newport, New York, and New Haven.
    - "Farmington Memory Book", 1917–1919 (Box 21)
      Covers activities at Miss Porter's School; contains printed ephemera, notes and letters from friends, and five pages of photographs of students. Much of the memorabilia relates to theatrical activities at the school.
  - Writings
    - On Wilmarth Lewis, 1935–1958 (Box 22, Folder 1)
      Primarily the prepared remarks delivered at their wedding anniversary events.
    - On Elizabeth Ellen Auchincloss (1844-1925), undated (Box 22, Folder 2)
      Memoir of her "Aunt Ellie."
    - On Annie Burr Jennings (1855-1939), undated (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - On a great university library, undated (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Other Papers
    - Baby book, 1902–1903 (Box 22, Folder 5)
      Contains a photograph as an infant and manuscript entries made through October 1903.
    - The Ghosts of My Friends, 1911 (Box 22, Folder 6)
      Autograph book signed by family and friends from 1911-1929.
    - Baptism certificate, Madison Avenue Presbyterian Church, 1918 January 6 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Daisy from marshal staff (Miss Porter's School), 1920 June 5 (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Birth certificates (certified copies), 1920 (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - Theatre programs, Paris, circa 1922 (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - United States passports, 1926–1950 (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - Wedding invitation and marriage certificate, 1928 (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - Wedding gifts register, 1928 (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - Munson Steamship Lines "Order of the Trident" certificates for travel on the SS American Legion, 1928 February 6 (Box 54 (Oversize), Folder 9)
      The certificates were issued to Annie and Wilmarth Lewis while onboard the steamship SS American Legion, which carried passengers and cargo in Munson's South American service. The Lewises began their honeymoon in to (or from) Rio de Janeiro, Brazil.
    - Souvenir postcard and photograph books from Rio de Janeiro, 1928 (Box 22, Folder 14)
      The Lewises traveled to Brazil on the first part of their honeymoon.
    - Blank notebook, undated (Box 22, Folder 15)
      Small blank book with a mirror and pencil, in a paper case; inscribed on the second leaf, "Mrs. Wray's Present to her Husband" and below that, "Mr. Lewis's present to his wife. London April 1928." Mr. Wray is possibly Sir Cecil Wray (1734-1805). The mirror was broken when found (2017).
    - Address books for London, Paris, and New York, circa 1930 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      Three leather-bound address books in a leather-covered case.
    - Hart-Deming house, 80 Main St., Farmington
      The "Red House" was purchased by Annie Lewis in 1930, rented out as a bookshop in the 1930s, and given to Miss Porter's School in the late 1940s.
      The files hold deeds and other records regarding repairs, paint colors, and renovations, including blueprints for a doorway and fireplace moulding by New Haven architect Douglas Orr. Also present is a May 15, 1930, issue of the Farmington Valley Herald with a related article about the use of part of the property for a proposed fire station.
      - Correspondence and records, 1930–1958 (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - Farmington Valley Herald, 1930 May 15 (Box 53 (Oversize), Folder 2)
      - Douglas Orr blueprints, 1931 (Box 54 (Oversize), Folder 4)
    - Bookplate, circa 1930 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      The file holds Carl Rollins's original artwork for a bookplate he designed for Annie Lewis, with a sample of a bookplate of a different design using Rollins's lettering.
    - Wills and codicils, 1937–1959 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Barney, Laura Dunham, 1940 (Box 23, Folder 5)
      Funeral service program and newspaper clipping.
    - Stationery, circa 1940 (Box 23, Folder 6)
      Samples of her printed letter paper, postcards, calling cards, mailing label, and paper hang tag.
    - Notes on dogs, 1941, undated (Box 23, Folder 7)
      Contains licenses and recommended diets.
    - Address books and lists, 1947, undated (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Hammacher Schlemmer orders, 1947–1955 (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Henri Bendel, Inc., 1954–1960 (Box 24, Folder 1)
      Concerning storage and disposition of furs.
    - Garden notes, 1954, 1956 (Box 24, Folder 2-3)
    - Customs paperwork, 1957 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Notes to Janet Sharp, 1958 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Photography ephemera, 1918–1950s (Box 24, Folder 6)
      Mailing bags, negative and print wallets and envelopes, and other ephemera from the Pavelle Laboratories and Eastman Kodak companies.
    - Other ephemera, 1921–1937, undated (Box 24, Folder 7)
      Dance card from Cambridge University social, membership cards, and other ephemera.
    - Drawings and sketches, undated (Box 53 (Oversize), Folder 3)
      Watercolor and graphite sketches of figures, landscapes, and the New Library (exterior).
- Family Papers, 1849–1960; Series III; 6.76; 8 boxes
  Series III is organized into three subseries: Genealogical Materials, Emma Brewster Jennings Auchincloss Papers, and Annie Burr Jennings Papers.
  The series consists of three groups of material: genealogical records of the Auchincloss, Burr, Jennings, and Nash families; papers of Emma Brewster Jennings Auchincloss; and papers of Annie Burr Jennings. The latter two groups contain some correspondence, ephemera, and Emma Auchincloss's photograph album from her time at Miss Porter's School. Also present are estate records for the Jennings sisters that include detailed inventories of their three homes in Connecticut and New York City; the inventories provide an important window on the material culture environment in which Annie Lewis was raised, as well as a record of the furnishings and decorative objects she brought into her own two homes after their deaths.
  - Genealogical Materials
    - Auchincloss family genealogy and other notes, 1902–1947, undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Auchincloss/Gurdon family genealogy, undated (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Auchincloss family trees, undated (Box 58 (Oversize), Folder 4)
      Two printed family trees, possibly removed from a publication.
    - Burr family chart, circa 1910 (Box 54 (Oversize), Folder 5)
      Family chart drawn and illuminated by Charles L. N. Camp of New Haven, an artist and professional genealogist who specialized in designing and producing coats-of-arms and family charts. It traces the family from Jehue Burr (1625-1692) to Annie Burr Auchincloss, and encompasses the Goodsell, Jennings, and ten other families related by marriage, all represented by family crests.
    - Jennings Ancestral Register, undated (Box 59 (Broadside))
      Two printed fan charts published by Frank Farnsworth Starr of Middletown, Connecticut, and filled with names in an unidentified hand; one register was created for Annie Burr Jennings and one for Emma Jennings Auchincloss.
    - Jennings family genealogy, 1941–1952, undated (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Nash family genealogy, undated (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Emma Brewster Jennings Auchincloss Papers
    Emma Brewster Jennings Auchincloss (1861-1942), a philanthropist, was the mother of Annie Lewis. The second of the five children of Oliver Burr Jennings and Esther Judson Goodsell Jennings, she was born in San Francisco, raised in New York and Fairfield, Connecticut, attended Miss Porter's School, and married a New York merchant, Hugh D. Auchincloss (1858-1913), in 1891. The couple raised their son and two daughters in New York and Newport, Rhode Island. Some years after her husband's death, Emma Auchincloss built a home, Dormy House on Sasco Hill Road in Fairfield, Connecticut, and died there at the age of 80.
    - Photograph album, circa 1880-1890 (Box 26 (Oversize))
      Likely assembled by Emma Jennings, the album begins with images of Farmington, Connecticut, followed by images of Sarah Porter, her school, students, class pictures, and reunions; and an image of the Memento Mori Cemetery cenotaph erected in memory Porter School art instructor Sarah Strong Tuthill (1830-1882). Following a series of blank leaves, a second group of ten pages of photographs of young women begins with a photograph of Celia Jennings. A third grouping of twenty-four pages begins with images of Fairfield, family scenes, pictures of dogs, sail boats, horse and buggies, pictures of interiors, groups of friends and family (some people are identified).
      Bound in three-quarters green morocco; spine split.
      Former call number: LWL Mss Vol. 201
    - Letters, 1913 (Box 25, Folder 5)
      Letters to Emma Auchincloss from the Farmington Lodge Society (Miss Porter's School) and the Kingsley Trust Association regarding the death of Hugh D. Auchincloss.
    - Stock accounts record book, 1916–1929 (Box 25, Folder 6)
      Records kept, in an unknown hand, of stocks purchased and sold for members of the Jennings, Auchincloss, and Lewis families
    - American Red Cross Military Hospital, 1918 (Box 25, Folder 7)
      Letter from hospital staff enclosing a letter from a French soldier occupying the bed endowed by Emma Auchincloss.
    - Heritage societies documents, 1936–1939 (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - New York Botanical Garden, 1951 May (Box 25, Folder 9)
      Photograph of a library dedication plaque listing Emma Auchincloss as a donor. (2018: plaque is in storage at the LuEsther T. Mertz Library.)
    - Obituary, 1942 (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - Estate records, 1942–1956 (Box 25, Folder 11-12)
    - Design for ledger stone, 1942 (Box 53 (Oversize), Folder 4)
      The gravestone is in Oaklawn Cemetery, Fairfield, Connecticut.
    - List of furniture, 1943 January 7 (Box 25, Folder 13)
      Inventory of furniture received by the Lewises from the Auchincloss house in Fairfield, Connecticut.
  - Annie Burr Jennings Papers
    Annie Burr Jennings (1855-1939) was an aunt of Annie Lewis, and the eldest of the five children of Oliver Burr Jennings and Esther Judson Goodsell Jennings. Born in San Francisco and raised in Fairfield, Connecticut, she attended Fairfield Academy and Miss Porter's School. Annie Jennings never married, and devoted her life to family, collecting, and history, with a particular interest in eighteenth-century American history. She served for many years as Vice Regent for Connecticut in the Mount Vernon Ladies' Association of the Union, a position to which she was nominated by her friend William Howard Taft. She filled her two homes in New York City and in Fairfield with her collections of prints, books, china, and silver; the latter residence, called "Sunnie-Holme," was noted for its extensive gardens which were open to the public. Jennings was a renowned philanthropist in both New York and Connecticut, and died at Sunnie-Holme at the age of 83.
    - Correspondence
      - Mount Vernon Ladies' Association, 1915, 1929–1937 (Box 27, Folder 1-2, Box 54 (Oversize), Folder 6)
        Correspondence, ephemera, and Annie Jennings's 1915 certificate appointing her Vice Regent of the State of Connecticut.
      - Perry, Loretta and Lewis Goodsell, 1935 (Box 27, Folder 3)
        Letters regarding Goodsell genealogy.
      - Yale University Library, 1927–1938 (Box 27, Folder 4)
      - Other correspondence, 1932–1938 (Box 27, Folder 5)
        A group of disparate letters from friends and colleagues to Jennings, with a Christmas greeting from Sunnie-Holme.
    - Annie Burr Jennings Ancestral Notes, I to XLI, undated (Box 56)
      Manuscript volume of biographies and genealogy.
    - Burr portraits, undated (Box 27, Folder 6)
      Mounted photographs of Aaron Burr portraits by Gilbert Stuart, John Vanderlyn (2), James Van Dyck, and Henry Inman, and a Theodosia Burr Alston portrait by John Vanderlyn (1811). The photographs were formerly in frames and each has a typed description from John E. Stillwell's book The History of the Burr Portraits (1928).
    - Diary of a trip to Italy, 1922 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - List of Shrubs and Plants…grown in Sunnie-Holme Herb Garden, 1938 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Recipe book, 1875 (Box 27, Folder 9)
      Manuscript notes in one volume of about one hundred cooking recipes for breads, pastries, sandwiches, and meat dishes. Pasted in at the end of the volume are fifteen pages of recipes cut from newspapers. The volume is inscribed inside the front cover: "Annie B Jennings / 1875."
      Custodial History
      Former call number: LWL Mss Vol. 13
    - United States Constitution Sesquicentennial Commission 1937 (Box 53 (Oversize), Folder 5)
    - Valentine, 1849 (Box 27, Folder 10)
      Embossed paper and satin valentine with a letter dated August 1849, both addressed to "Mr. Shipman" enclosed in an early twentieth-century envelope stating the letter was "supposedly written" by Esther Judson Goodsell.
    - William Howard Taft
      William Howard Taft was a student at Yale with Walter Jennings (1858–1933), the brother of Annie and Emma Jennings, and both men were members of Skull and Bones. Taft also taught at Yale from 1913 until he joined the United States Supreme Court in 1921.
      - Correspondence, 1912–1930 (Box 27, Folder 11)
        Autograph letters, and typed letters, signed, from Taft to Annie Jennings; also present is one letter from Helen Taft.
      - Banquet program, Yale University graduates dinner, 1909 March 19 (Box 27, Folder 12)
        The dinner was held at the Waldorf Astoria in New York; inscribed: "For Miss Annie Jennings / with affectionate regard of Wm H. Taft / March 19-1909."
      - Newspaper clippings, 1907–1930 (Box 27, Folder 13-16, Box 54 (Oversize), Folder 7)
      - Portrait photograph, 1908 (Box 57 (Oversize))
        A mounted half-length portrait by Isaac Benjamin, Cincinnati; inscribed on mount below image: "For my friend Miss Annie Jennings / with best wishes / Wm H Taft"; in a double-sided display frame made by D. B. Butler & Co., New York.
    - Portrait of Benito Mussolini, 1927 March 5 (Box 54 (Oversize), Folder 8)
      A half-length portrait of Benito Mussolini mounted on a sheet of card; he is holding a sheaf of paper. "FOT V LAVIOSA/ROMA" is printed in the upper left corner. "CONCESS PANDIMIGLIO-38 CAFO LE CASE-ROMA" is printed at the lower left and "REPRODUZIONE VIRTATA-DEPOSITATA" is printed at the lower right. Inscribed in ink on the card mount: "A Miss Annie Burr / Roma marzo 1927 V Mussolini."
    - Estate records
      - Will, 1939 (Box 28, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence and distribution lists, 1939–1942 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      - Fairfield probate court account, 1939 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - Jennings Beach property, 1939–1950 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - Inventory, 9 East 70th St., New York, 1939 (Box 28, Folder 5)
      - Inventory, "Sunnie Holme," Fairfield, Connecticut, 1939 (Box 28, Folder 6)